<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: race report | Guillaume Calmettes]]></title>
  <link href="http://gcalmettes.github.io/blog/categories/race-report/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://gcalmettes.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-17T19:07:05-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://gcalmettes.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Guillaume Calmettes]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[guillaume.calmettes@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Chimera 100M 2013 - Race Report]]></title>
    <link href="http://gcalmettes.github.io/blog/2013/12/05/Chimera2013/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-05T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://gcalmettes.github.io/blog/2013/12/05/Chimera2013</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>   <p>
   <img  src="http://gcalmettes.github.io/images/chimera-logo.jpg" alt="Chimera Logo"
   width=30%"width" height="height" style="float:right;margin:0 0 5px 20px;" />
   Chimera 100M took place in the Saddleback Mountains, CA, a few miles away from Lake Elsinore.
   Knowing part of the trails I went in with the conscious knowledge that this was not going
   to be an easy run, as Chimera is one of the toughest 100 miler in Southern California, on par
   with <a href="http://www.ac100.com/">Angeles Crest 100</a>. Being a rookie on the distance, I was not
   sure of what to expect, but I was more than eager to see how I could handle it.
   This year, we had the pleasure of running on a new beefed-up course, 10mi of fireroad
   having been replaced by 11mi of technical trails. The changes resulted in
   an added 1000ft to the already 22000ft elevation gain of the race.
   In addition Chimera is notorious for its bad weather, and as expected, the sunny +70F weather
   we enjoyed during the preceding week transformed into a low 40F rainy forecast on race day.
   </p></p>

<p>  <div style="width:image width px; font-size:80%; text-align:center;">
  <img src="http://gcalmettes.github.io/images/chimera2013-profile.jpg" alt="home made marthon splits"
  width=95%"width" height="height" style="padding-bottom:0.5em; padding-top:0.5em;" />
  <br/>New profile of the Chimera 100M race
  </div></p>

<p><strong>Sugarloaf loop (0-11mi, 1:35)</strong></p>

<p>While the sun was coming out at Bluejay Campground, Steve Harvey, the race director,
invited all the runners
to gather on the starting line to be ready for the 6:30AM race start, and gave his final
words of wisdom. It was cold and pouring rain, but I couldn&rsquo;t wait to be running!</p>

<p>  <div style="width:image width px; font-size:80%; text-align:center;">
  <img src="http://gcalmettes.github.io/images/chimera2013-start.jpg" alt="home made marthon splits"
  width=95%"width" height="height" style="padding-bottom:0.5em; padding-top:0.5em;" />
  <br/>&ldquo;At least it won&rsquo;t be dusty&rdquo; &ndash; Steve Harvey, RD &ndash;
  </div></p>

<p>The race started, and after half a mile a group of 4 of us had already made a gap on the
rest of the field. <a href="http://www.fabricerun.com/">Fabrice Hardel</a>, the past two years winner of the event,
was of course in front, and he was leading the group on what I thought was a very
comfortable pace. The other runners were Igor Campos, the freshly new record holder of
<a href="http://www.cuyamaca100k.com">Cuyamaca 100km</a>, and Jonathan Landis, who had passed me in the final 3 miles
at Cuyamaca 100km.
We were soon joined by Brian Peterson, winner of the gnarly
<a href="http://www.runlospinos.com">Los Pinos 50km</a> this year, and the 5 of us stayed together for the first loop
of the race.
This loop was the new addition of the race, 11 miles of technical trails, with
some fun rolling little hills. The rain was making the trails a bit slippery, but my
NB 1010v2 were doing a good job of keeping me on track. We were still going at a very
casual pace, all chatting, and it felt like doing a training run with friends.
The miles flew by, and we were already back to Bluejay Campground where I took off my
AK pack and switched over to one handheld filled with a protein/carb mix that my crew,
Pauline and <a href="http://www.dominicgrossman.com">Dom</a>, had already prepared for me.</p>

<p><strong>Candy Store lollipop (11-33mi, 3:36)</strong></p>

<p>The next 22 miles were a big out-and-back lollipop. 11 miles down 11 miles up
on a technical single track. The first 6 miles of the long downhill drove us
in the middle of the forest up to Chiquita Falls Aid Station.
The 5 of us were still running together, like a well oiled train,
and I was feeling really good, running just behind <a href="http://www.fabricerun.com/">Fabrice</a>.
After the aid station, where nobody stopped, the run opened and we could enjoy the
surrounding cloudy mountainous landscape.</p>

<p>  <div style="width:image width px; font-size:80%; text-align:center;">
  <img src="http://gcalmettes.github.io/images/chimera2013-train.jpg" alt="home made marthon splits"
  width=95%"width" height="height" style="padding-bottom:0.5em; padding-top:0.5em;" />
  <br/> The Chimera Train Express, tracked by the french locomotive
  </div></p>

<p>We finally got to the bottom and the Candy Store Aid Station, where we could see our crew.
Helped by Pauline and Dom, I unloaded some clothes and exchanged my bottles in a flash
before going after Fabrice who did not even stop to refill.</p>

<p>  <div style="width:image width px; font-size:80%; text-align:center;">
  <img src="http://gcalmettes.github.io/images/chimera2013-candystore.jpg" alt="home made marthon splits"
  width=60%"width" height="height" style="padding-bottom:0.5em; padding-top:0.5em;" />
  <br/> Quick transition at the Candy Store AS before going after Fabrice
  </div></p>

<p>This is where we made a small gap on Igor, Brian and Jonathan who all stopped longer
at the AS. Our lead did not last for
long though, as Jonathan caught us and took off half a mile later at the beginning of the
climb when Fabrice and I were on a pee stop. To be honest, I was kind of surprised by such
a move this early in the race and I was eager to engage a chase but I finally changed
my mind and just kept the good pace we were running at in the climb.
This part was a lot of fun and I really enjoyed running it with Fabrice,
exchanging turns and chatting in French. I guess this was kind of a remake of
the <a href="http://ultra.irunfar.com/wp-content/uploads/2013-Hardrock-100-Joe-Grant-Sebastien-Chaigneau-Grouse-Gulch.jpg">Joe and Seb french-speaking duo</a> earlier this year at Hardrock 100.
We ran consistently, and near the top of the climb we re-passed Jonathan who had switched to
a run/power-hike mode. The next couple of miles flew by, and after 5h15 and 33mi into the race,
we arrived at Bluejay again.
This would be the last time we see our crew before the Silverado Aid Station (mile 60)
where we could also pick up our pacers.</p>

<p><strong>Bluejay to Silverado, Santiago Peak #1 (33-60mi, 5:24)</strong></p>

<p>The rain had stopped and I wanted to take some time at the AS to put warm clothes and
change my socks. The stop ended up being way shorter than anticipated as my crew was
over-energized by I don&rsquo;t know what and got me dry and ready in record time! As a result,
I left Bluejay 5min ahead of everybody else, feeling really good and enjoying the moment.</p>

<p>  <div style="width:image width px; font-size:80%; text-align:center;">
  <img src="http://gcalmettes.github.io/images/chimera2013-firstplace.jpg" alt="home made marthon splits"
  width=95%"width" height="height" style="padding-bottom:0.5em; padding-top:0.5em;" />
  <br/> Formula Uno pit stop = One happy runner leading the race after 33mi
  </div></p>

<p>Dom ran with me until the start of the Trabuco climb, giving me some tips on how to
run the next section. I ran the whole climb at constant pace and did not even stop at
the AS at the top as I wanted to bank as much time as possible on Fabrice, knowing that
he would be right on my heels very soon. I entered the very rocky single track of the Tracbuco
trail descent and ran the 6 miles of it as smooth as I could.
Technical descents are generally not where I shine, but I was pretty happy with how
I handled this one. In fact, at the <a href="http://laurenontherun.blogspot.com/2013/11/holy-jim-aid-chimera-2013.html">Holy Jim AS</a> at the bottom I
still had the same 5min lead on Fabrice. As this point, Brian was just 20min behind him.</p>

<p>  <div style="width:image width px; font-size:80%; text-align:center;">
  <img src="http://gcalmettes.github.io/images/chimera2013-holyjim.jpg" alt="home made marthon splits"
  width=95%"width" height="height" style="padding-bottom:0.5em; padding-top:0.5em;" />
  <br/> Quick water sip at Holy Jim AS with Fabrice just 5min behind
  (photo by <a href="http://laurenontherun.blogspot.com/2013/11/holy-jim-aid-chimera-2013.html">Lauren</a>)
  </div></p>

<p>I quickly drank two glasses of water and took off to run one of my favorite part of the race,
the Holy Jim Climb. I love long climbs, and I was excited to see how I would be able to run
this one with 40mi already on my legs. As I started to climb, I recalled what Dom told me
earlier, to run the first half consistently and try to make a push on the second half.
The switchbacks of the beginning of the climb were a lot of fun to run on.</p>

<p>  <div style="width:image width px; font-size:80%; text-align:center;">
  <img src="http://gcalmettes.github.io/images/chimera2013-climb.jpg" alt="home made marthon splits"
  width=95%"width" height="height" style="padding-bottom:0.5em; padding-top:0.5em;" />
  <br/> Enjoying some nice running in the SaddleBack Mountains
  </div></p>

<p>For the second half, I tried to push a bit, but I guess my legs started to feel a bit tired
because I did not have the impression that I was going any faster. I was still moving
well though,
that was the most important. However, at 3mi of the summit of Santiago Peak, I looked
back and got a glimpse of Fabrice gaining on me very rapidly.
2min later, we were running together again and we will do so until the summit.
It was actually nice to have some company at the summit, because it was
very cold and foggy. On the next downhill, I realized that Fabrice had better legs than me
at that point, because I had to push a bit to try to stay with him. He slowly got ahead
and arrived 5min before me at the Maple Spring AS (mile 53).</p>

<p>  <div style="width:image width px; font-size:80%; text-align:center;">
  <img src="http://gcalmettes.github.io/images/chimera2013-maplesprings.jpg" alt="home made marthon splits"
  width=60%"width" height="height" style="padding-bottom:0.5em; padding-top:0.5em;" />
  <br/> Maple Springs AS with Fabrice. Just happy to be here (photo by Trisha Tighe)
  </div></p>

<p>When I arrived at Maple Spring, he had already finished to change his shoes and
was taking in some calories. The volunteers were amazing, and we even got a picture
together. I quickly traded my 1010v2 for my NB 1400v2, more suited for
the fireroad-like terrain of the second half of the race, and we left the AS together.
I could not keep up with him in the long downhill and I had to slow down as my legs
were actually giving me some real pain.
I knew that my crew was waiting at the bottom, and I was sorry to make them wait so long.
After what felt like eternity, I entered the road section of the last 2mi
of the downhill. This downhill was really beating me, and I just wanted to be done with it.
I tried to play mind games, that helped, but not that much.
Finally, as I was approaching the bottom, I got the surprise to see <a href="https://twitter.com/theobalestra">Théo</a>
and Lola waiting for me to run with me the last couple hundreds yards before the Silverado
AS. This gave me a great mental boost, and I was feeling good again!
Once at the aid station, I was glad to see everybody. <a href="http://instagram.com/cbalestra">Christophe</a>, Christelle,
Aidan, Théo, Lola, Dom, Pauline, and even <a href="http://ievenranthisfar.tumblr.com">Andy</a> who made a
10h trip from NYC just to cheer on me. I was stocked to see all my friends
and this gave me even more motivation to give my best for the rest of the race.
I would have loved to stay longer with them, but the clock was ticking and it was time
to chase Fabrice. He had left the aid station 15min before and from what my friends told
me he was looking very good, but who knows, 40mi left is still a long way and a lot can
happen.
In addition, I was now running with my first pacer, <a href="http://www.dominicgrossman.com">Dom, aka the Unicorn</a>,
and I knew he would give me all the pep talk I would need to keep me on track.</p>

<p>  <div style="width:image width px; font-size:80%; text-align:center;">
  <img src="http://gcalmettes.github.io/images/chimera2013-silverado.jpg" alt="home made marthon splits"
  width=95%"width" height="height" style="padding-bottom:0.5em; padding-top:0.5em;" />
  <br/> IN and OUT of the Silverado AS. Glad we got some good news at the check out!
  </div></p>

<p><strong>Silverado to Corona, Santiago Peak #2 (60-85mi, 5:15)</strong></p>

<p>The next section started with 2.5mi of uphill single track until the top of Bedford Peak. From
there, we would have to run some rolling hills and climb up to the top of Santiago Peak
again before running the long descent of Corona canyon.
As the night was settling down, we enjoyed a great moonrise on the mountains.
35min into the climb we heard some cheering at the bottom, and we saw two headlamps
running into the Silverado AS, probably the 3rd and 4th runners. That was the first time
I had any kind of information about the runners behind me. I was alternating slow shuffle
and power-hike, trying to keep my effort constant in the climb.
We arrived at the aid station at the top of Bedford Peak and we got welcomed
by <a href="http://www.sandiego100.com">Scott Mills</a>. I took in some of their delicious chicken noodle soup and
we took off after they told us Fabrice was only 15min ahead.</p>

<p>  <div style="width:image width px; font-size:80%; text-align:center;">
  <img src="http://gcalmettes.github.io/images/chimera2013-bedfordpeak.jpg" alt="home made marthon splits"
  width=60%"width" height="height" style="padding-bottom:0.5em; padding-top:0.5em;" />
  <br/> Enjoying the moonrise on our way to Bedford Peak (photo by Dom)
  </div></p>

<p>I did my best to run as much as I could for the next miles, and we arrived at Maple
Spring for the second time of the day. Here, same routine, I took in some chicken noodle soup
and we were ready to go! As we were climbing to Santiago Peak, we were cheered on by
the runners going down to Silverado, it was great to see all those runners, and we even
saw <a href="https://twitter.com/erincha">Erin</a>, looking good in her second 100 miler after having finished <a href="http://www.ac100.com/">AC100</a>
few months ago.</p>

<p>  <div style="width:image width px; font-size:80%; text-align:center;">
  <img src="http://gcalmettes.github.io/images/chimera2013-night.jpg" alt="home made marthon splits"
  width=95%"width" height="height" style="padding-bottom:0.5em; padding-top:0.5em;" />
  <br/> Into the night at Chimera 100 (photos by Dom)
  </div></p>

<p>We finally tagged the top of Santiago Peak, it was cold and dark and there was no view
to really enjoy, so we didn&rsquo;t wasted time and started the long 12mi descent. Trust me, 73mi
into a race, long descents are not that fun. I was starting to have some serious
pain again in my legs, but Dom was giving me some good advices to run smoothly and limit
the damages. We rapidly stopped at the Indian Truck AS (&ldquo;give me more of that soup!&rdquo;)
and went for the last 6.5mi of the descent that I will have to climb up later with my
second pacer, Christophe, once at the Corona AS. The pain in ultras is part of the game,
so I was trying to keep smiling and enjoy the moment, there is nothing as great as running
with friends in the mountains!
At 1mi of the bottom, we crossed Fabrice who was already going up, he was still looking very
good and we cheered on each others. Few minutes later, Dom and I got to the Corona AS,
and I got welcomed by even more friends as <a href="http://breakingexcellent.blogspot.com">Katie</a> had also arrived to join the group.</p>

<p>  <div style="width:image width px; font-size:80%; text-align:center;">
  <img src="http://gcalmettes.github.io/images/chimera2013-corona.jpg" alt="home made marthon splits"
  width=50%"width" height="height" style="padding-bottom:0.5em; padding-top:0.5em;" />
  <br/> Just 15mi left! Still smiling at Corona AS.
  </div></p>

<p><strong>Corona to Finish (85-100mi, 4:29)</strong></p>

<p>I left the Corona AS with <a href="http://instagram.com/cbalestra">Christophe</a> and we started the climb back to the
indian truck trail aid station. The climb was only a 7% grade, but I had really hard time to run
it. At that point, I knew that it would be very hard to close the gap with Fabrice and I
started to become worried about keeping my second place. At the bottom of the climb, I was
wondering if a sub-19h finish was possible, but after the first half of the climb I was going
so slow that I was wondering if a sub-20h finish was even possible.
We crossed Brian
who was coming down to Corona, and Christophe told me we had about 1h15 on him. We finally
got to the top where we cheered on more runners coming down.</p>

<p>  <div style="width:image width px; font-size:80%; text-align:center;">
  <img src="http://gcalmettes.github.io/images/chimera2013-itt.jpg" alt="home made marthon splits"
  width=95%"width" height="height" style="padding-bottom:0.5em; padding-top:0.5em;" />
  <br/> The ITT aid station!
  </div></p>

<p>After a quick stop at the ITT aid station, we went for the last 9mi of the race. I had done
this section during a training run, but I didn&rsquo;t remember how steep the remaining hills
of the main divide road were.
Even with all the cheering of Christophe, I was not able to move very fast
and I walked most of them. My quads were burning and the downhills were not easier.
We passed the horsethief AS and walked more steep hills. Finally, we got to the last AS at
the top of the Trabuco Trail, and I had the surprise to see Jorge and Maria there!
They told us we were just 2mi from the finish. Everything was painful, but I was very happy
to be here.
Christophe was still thinking that
a sub-20h finish time was a realistic goal and in a final attempt to make me move
faster, he told me that some French macaroons were waiting for me at the finish line and that
the faster I would go, the sooner I could taste them ;)
His trick didn&rsquo;t have much effect on my slowness and we ended up crossing the finish line
in a time of 20:19:13.</p>

<p>I was pumped up, all my friends were there, and they welcomed me with a Champagne shower!
I couldn&rsquo;t have been more happy.</p>

<p>  <div style="width:image width px; font-size:80%; text-align:center;">
  <img src="http://gcalmettes.github.io/images/chimera2013-finish.jpg" alt="home made marthon splits"
  width=95%"width" height="height" style="padding-bottom:0.5em; padding-top:0.5em;" />
  <br/> Champagne shower at the finish line
  </div></p>

<p>  <div style="width:image width px; font-size:80%; text-align:center;">
  <img src="http://gcalmettes.github.io/images/chimera2013-postrace.jpg" alt="home made marthon splits"
  width=95%"width" height="height" style="padding-bottom:0.5em; padding-top:0.5em;" />
  <br/> Post-race celebration with friends
  </div></p>

<p>I&rsquo;m extremely grateful to my crew and friends who all believed in me during
the race. I couldn&rsquo;t have done it without their support. Thank you all!</p>

<p><strong>What I used during the race</strong></p>

<p><em>Nutrition</em></p>

<ul>
<li>Powerbar gels (35, w/ caffeine after 60mi)</li>
<li>Powerbar protein bars (5, one every 3-4h)</li>
<li>Powerbar recovery drink (at each AS w/ crew)</li>
</ul>


<p><em>Gear</em></p>

<ul>
<li>Ultimate Direction AK vest</li>
<li>Amphipod handhelds</li>
<li>The North Face Verto pro jacket</li>
<li>Salomon Exo S-Lab Twinskin short</li>
<li>New Balance MT1010v2 (0-53mi)</li>
<li>New Balance MR1400v2 (53-100mi)</li>
<li>Petzl Myo RXP</li>
</ul>


<p>See you next year!</p>

<p>  <div style="width:image width px; font-size:80%; text-align:center;">
  <img src="http://gcalmettes.github.io/images/chimera2013-belt.jpg" alt="home made marthon splits"
  width=60%"width" height="height" style="padding-bottom:0.5em; padding-top:0.5em;" />
  <br/> Chimera Belt
  </div></p>

<hr />
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Los Angeles Marathon 2013 - Race Report]]></title>
    <link href="http://gcalmettes.github.io/blog/2013/03/24/LAM2013/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://gcalmettes.github.io/blog/2013/03/24/LAM2013</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My goal for this 28th edition of the LA Marathon was ambitious (at least for me ;)):
I wanted to run a sub-3h marathon.
I knew it wouldn&rsquo;t be easy as that would imply to shave almost 26min off my marathon PR
(3:25:39, set at the LA marathon 2012), but I guess we also run to overcome challenges
like that no? However I had the feeling that this goal was attainable
after all the training I went through in the past few months to prepare for the
<a href="http://gcalmettes.github.io/blog/2012/12/05/TNF50K/">TNFC 50K</a> and the <a href="http://gcalmettes.github.io/blog/2013/02/20/Bandit50K/">Bandit Ultra Run 50K</a>.
I was aware that I hadn&rsquo;t really done my homeworks of road specific training, having mostly
focused on trail running for the past 6 months,
but I was doing this race for the 2 on the clock
at the finish line, so basically I wanted to have my cake and eat it too.</p>

<p>This marathon was also special in the sense that I had some family visiting from France,
and David (brother in law) had registered to the race in an attempt to run (and hopefully
finish) his first marathon!
Therefore, I was really excited to share with him the LA marathon route which
showcases Los Angeles and the cities beautifully with its
<a href="http://www.lamarathon.com/event/course-map/">“Stadium to the Sea”</a> route.
The race is a lot of fun and a great way to visit Los Angeles,
beginning at Dodger Stadium and running through famous
cities and landmarks like Chinatown, Hollywood Blvd, the Sunset Strip and Rodeo Drive,
before ending at the Beach near the famous Santa Monica Pier.</p>

<p>On the day before the race, we went to the race expo to pick up our bibs.
I loved the atmosphere there, it was electric and we could really feel the excitement
people at the expo had for the race. We stopped by most of the sponsor booths and grabbed
a ton of goodies ;)</p>

<p>  <div style="width:image width px; font-size:80%; text-align:center;">
  <img src="http://gcalmettes.github.io/images/lam2013-expo.jpeg" alt="LA marathon exposition"
  width=80%"width" height="height" style="padding-bottom:0.5em;" />
  <br/>With David at the pre-race exposition
  </div></p>

<p><strong>The plan</strong></p>

<p>If you search on the internet, you will find that there are a lot of recommended strategies
to run a sub-3h marathon. Some call for a first slow five miles, followed by
running on pace until mile 20, then a fast close.
Others prefer negative splits where the first half is just slightly slower than the second
half. Some describe just even splits.
The problem was that even if I was in one of the better running shape of my life,
from my previous experience with the marathon distance it was
hard for me to imagine a finish as strong (even splits) or even stronger (negative splits)
than the first part of the race. So in the end my plan was just to run the first half in
more or less 1:28:XX so I would have roughly 4min to spare in the second half. I though it was
also a good idea since
the second half has more downhills, so in the case I cannot sustain the pace
the downhills would help to limit any time damage.</p>

<p>  <div style="width:image width px; font-size:80%; text-align:center;">
  <img src="http://gcalmettes.github.io/images/lam2013-profile.jpg" alt="LA marathon profile"
  width=100%"width" height="height" style="padding-bottom:0.5em;" />
  <br/>Elevation profile of the LA marathon.
  </div></p>

<p>The LA marathon was just 4 weeks after the <a href="http://gcalmettes.github.io/blog/2013/02/20/Bandit50K/">Bandit 50K</a>.
In between, I focused on doing some race specific trainings on road, such as
<a href="http://app.strava.com/activities/42341358">intervals trainings</a> during the week
and long tempo-ish runs on the week-ends (<a href="http://app.strava.com/activities/42181890">#1</a> and <a href="http://app.strava.com/activities/42867616">#2</a>).
I then did for the first time a proper taper on the two last weeks leading to
the race.</p>

<p>  <div style="width:image width px; font-size:80%; text-align:center;">
  <img src="http://gcalmettes.github.io/images/lam2013-armsplit.jpg" alt="home made marthon splits"
  width=80%"width" height="height" style="padding-bottom:0.5em;" />
  <br/>My home-made pace band
  </div></p>

<p><strong>The story</strong></p>

<p>I didn&rsquo;t sleep well the night before the marathon, probably a
mix of pressure and excitement.
After a quick breakfast, David and I headed out to Santa Monica to take the 5:30AM shuttle
and we arrived at the Dodgers stadium with more than one hour
to spare.</p>

<p>There was a lot of runners already there, and the conditions looked perfect.</p>

<p>40min before the start, I made my way to the corral B (previous sub-4h marathon finisher).
Last year, I showed up too late and
the corral access was already closed, so at least this year I didn&rsquo;t do the same mistake.
While waiting for the start, I chatted with some legacy runners, those guys are
amazing and clearly know how to share their passion for the
LA marathon. After some nice chats with my new friends, the gun went off,
and suddenly we were running!</p>

<p>I started a bit faster than the planned pace,
but I wasn&rsquo;t too much worried about it as the first 3 miles of the race are basically all
downhill and I wanted to bank some time before the first hills anyways.</p>

<pre><code>Mile 1 - 6:32
Mile 2 - 6:34
Mile 3 - 6:46
</code></pre>

<p>In the next section we hit a good amount of hills.
I ran them at a very conservative pace to limit my energy expenditure.
Even if it was kind of early for a Sunday morning, there was a lot of spectators cheering
on the runners, especially on this section, and that was clearly a mental boost for me!
By mile 6, I was right on pace and the major hills of the day were already behind me.
I crossed the 10km mark in 42:24, a bit behind schedule but feeling really good.</p>

<pre><code>Mile 4 - 6:51
Mile 5 - 7:03
Mile 6 - 6:52
</code></pre>

<p>Miles 7-14 were basically all flat.
Nothing much happened here, except that I had to quickly stop to empty my bladder
right before entering Hollywood. I was running very relaxed, and my legs were responsive.
I hit the &frac12; marathon mark around 1:29:XX. This was a bit slower than what I
originally planned, but I was more than happy with it and I was
still confident about my sub-3h goal.</p>

<pre><code>Mile 7 - 6:36
Mile 8 - 6:44
Mile 9 - 6:48
Mile 10 - 6:43
Mile 11 - 6:38
Mile 12 - 6:40
Mile 13 - 6:47
Mile 14 - 6:45
</code></pre>

<p>We then ran through West Hollywood, followed by Beverly Hills.
At mile 17 we entered the famous Rodeo Drive where a huge crowd was supporting
the runners, spectators are amazing!
At that point, I noticed that I was passing runners just by keeping my pace.
I was still feeling really good, and those 3 miles flew by.</p>

<pre><code>Mile 15 - 6:26
Mile 16 - 6:38
Mile 17 - 6:53
</code></pre>

<p>We turned back on Santa Monica Blvd just to be cheered on by a huge assembly of
cheerleaders from various LA schools (the so called &ldquo;Cheer Alley&rdquo; landmark).
That was surrealistic,
they were screaming like crazy and I tried to pick up some of their energy to
run this long slightly uphill section of Santa Monica Blvd. At mile 20 we made
a right turn on Sepulveda Blvd, and started our way to enter the VA.</p>

<pre><code>Mile 18 - 6:44
Mile 19 - 6:36
Mile 20 - 6:40
</code></pre>

<p>At the VA entrance the <a href="http://www.clifbar.com">Cliff</a> booth was waiting for us, giving gels
to runners.
I took down two more gels and my energy level went up.
I looked at my watch, happily surprised by the time I was reading on it.
I was on a good track to achieve my sub-3h goal, and mentally at this point of the race
this was a huge boost. In addition, the route from the VA grounds to the finish
is pretty much my home/work neighborhood and I knew I was going to see a lot
of family and friends there, so I was more than ever eager to push myself and
pick up the pace for the
remaining miles.</p>

<pre><code>Mile 21 - 6:49
Mile 22 - 6:42
</code></pre>

<p>Passing the Brentwood Golf, I got cheered on by Pauline and my mother.
It was great to see them.</p>

<p>  <div style="width:image width px; font-size:80%; text-align:center;">
  <img src="http://gcalmettes.github.io/images/lam2013-withpauline.jpg" alt="LA marathon guillaume calmettes"
  width=80%"width" height="height" style="padding-bottom:0.5em;" />
  <br/>Accompanied by Pauline along the Brentwood Golf
  </div></p>

<p>My buddy Christophe was hanging out a little farther, and he ran with me for almost
half a mile. He took a bunch of pictures, including this one showing my
underwear-based marathon suit.</p>

<p>  <div style="width:image width px; font-size:80%; text-align:center;">
  <img src="http://gcalmettes.github.io/images/lam2013-mile23.jpg" alt="LA marathon guillaume calmettes"
  width=50%"width" height="height" style="padding-bottom:0.5em;" />
  <br/>Smiling and feeling really good with only 3 miles to go!
  </div></p>

<p>I also ran into <a href="http://j-tris.blogspot.com">Josh</a> that I had met at the Bandit 50K and who was
pacing some friends toward the finish.
I did my best to give everything I had left on San Vicente Blvd, and I am pretty sure I
experienced the <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/03/27/health/nutrition/27best.html">runner&rsquo;s high</a> on that section until the finish line,
because I never felt so good while running.</p>

<pre><code>Mile 23 - 6:38
Mile 24 - 6:31
Mile 25 - 6:33
Mile 26 - 6:23
0.35 mi - 5:30
</code></pre>

<p>I crossed the finish line in <strong>2:56:25</strong>, banking a new PR, and good enough
for 104 out of 23,016 finishers.</p>

<p>A huge congratulations to David for having finished his first marathon!
The second half was hard but he stayed focused and did it!</p>

<p>  <div style="width:image width px; font-size:80%; text-align:center;">
  <img src="http://gcalmettes.github.io/images/lam2013-medals.jpg" alt="LA marathon medals"
  width=80%"width" height="height" style="padding-bottom:0.5em;" />
  <br/>Happy marathoners
  </div></p>

<p><strong>The Aftermath</strong></p>

<p>I am super happy to have crushed my sub-3h goal.
This is the first time I finish a marathon feeling really great, and I am sure
this has something to do with my recent focus on trail running which forced me
to double my training volume.
In fact, I didn&rsquo;t realize that during the race, but looking at my official splits
I basically ran negative 10K splits the whole race, something I could imagine I
was able to.
An other interesting point is that my recovery after the marathon was super fast,
probably an other effect of my increase in volume training.</p>

<p>I can&rsquo;t wait to be back on the trails now!</p>

<p>  <div style="width:image width px; font-size:80%; text-align:center;">
  <img src="http://gcalmettes.github.io/images/lam2013-splits.jpg" alt="LA marathon guillaume calmettes splits"
  width=100%"width" height="height" style="padding-bottom:0.5em;" />
  </div></p>

<hr />
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bandit 50K 2013 - Race Report]]></title>
    <link href="http://gcalmettes.github.io/blog/2013/02/20/Bandit50K/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-20T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://gcalmettes.github.io/blog/2013/02/20/Bandit50K</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week end was held the <a href="http://banditultratrailrun.com">2013 Bandit Ultra Run 50K</a> in Simi Valley.
This race went into my radar few days after I finished the <a href="http://gcalmettes.github.io/blog/2012/12/05/TNF50K/">TNFC 50K</a>
while I was looking for a good race to start off 2013.
The Bandit 50K profile shows more elevation compared to the TNFC 50K, and consists of
2 long major climbs with 4 smaller climbs in between.</p>

<p>  <div style="width:image width px; font-size:80%; text-align:center;">
  <img src="http://gcalmettes.github.io/images/bandit50k-profile.jpg" alt="bandit 50K profile"
  width=80%"width" height="height" style="padding-bottom:0.5em;" />
  <br/>The Bandit 50K profile
  </div></p>

<p>My preparation for the race has not been optimal.
Early January, my back was blocked due to a vertebral displacement (T7).
Hopefully, after I went to a Doctor of Osteopathy, the slightly out-of-place
vertebrae was back into line and I was able to get back into running. The next two weeks,
wanting to make up
for lost time, I pushed myself a bit harder than usual. This may have
weakened my immune system, as I got hit by the flu the first week of February after
I went to Philadelphia to attend a conference.
I still managed to log some (slow-paced) miles
while recovering, which helped me to keep my morale high with the race approaching.</p>

<p>The day before the Bandit 50K, I went to rent a car
(yes I know it doesn&rsquo;t make sense to have been in LA for 2 years and to not
have a car yet ;) ), eager to have a good time on the trails the day after.
I woke up early and drove out to Simi Valley. A lot of runners were already there,
and they were all looking very strong.</p>

<p>The race started and I managed to stay at the back of the lead group for the &ldquo;warming loop&rdquo;
in Corriganville
Park. Trey Barnes (the defending champion) and <a href="http://ultrarunnerrn.blogspot.com">Chris Price</a> (the race record holder)
were setting the pace. I was not feeling very strong, but I was not feeling very weak either.</p>

<p>We reached the first climb and after we passed the tunnel under the 118,
<a href="http://ultrarunnerrn.blogspot.com">Chris Price</a> and <a href="http://jameswalshracing.com">James Walsh</a> started to pull ahead,
with Kenneth Ringled trying to
stay in contact with them. Halfway to the top I was surprised to find myself in 4th place
and I wondered if I wasn&rsquo;t going too fast considering what we will have to run for the
rest of the race. I hold back a little bit and I rapidly got passed by Keith Yanov and
then Chris Zurbuch who both looked very easy in the uphill.</p>

<p>  <div style="width:image width px; font-size:80%; text-align:center;">
  <img src="http://gcalmettes.github.io/images/bandit50k-firstclimb.jpg" alt="bandit 50K guillaume calmettes"
  width=80%"width" height="height" style="padding-bottom:0.5em;" />
  <br/>Halfway to the top of the first climb.
  <br/>Photo <a href="http://www.allwedoisrun.com">Luis Escobar</a></div></p>

<p>At the top of the climb I was a couple of hundreds feet behind Chris Z and Keith,
but the 3 leaders were already out of sight. We attacked the descent and hit the first major
aid station (Hawaiian theme!), but I didn&rsquo;t stop by as I had still plenty of water
and 3 gels in my pocket.
Right after the aid station we entered the Chumash trail, a long, snaking single-track
descent, with great scenic views over the Simi Valley mountains.
I loved every second of it and I had a lot of fun running it.</p>

<p>  <div style="width:image width px; font-size:80%; text-align:center;">
  <img src="http://gcalmettes.github.io/images/bandit50k-singletrack.jpg" alt="bandit 50K single track"
  width=60%"width" height="height" style="padding-bottom:0.5em;" />
  <br/>Having fun on a top-notch single track.<br/>Photo <a href="http://ericagratton.com">Erica Gratton</a></div></p>

<p>Approaching the end of the descent, I got passed by Matthew Ardine.
He was really fast in the downhill
but seemed to be less comfortable in the uphill as we constantly traded spots
back and forth for the next few miles,
me passing him on the climbs and him passing me in the descents.</p>

<p>We ran into the next aid station which was in a residential neighborhood and I re-filled up
my one handheld with water. The volunteers asked me how I was feeling, and I told
them I was feeling good and I was having a great time.
Right after the aid station however, I missed the right turn at the bottom of the &ldquo;Hot-Dog hill&rdquo;
(well maybe I was not feeling
so good finally, lol), but hopefully I was called back almost instantly by the volunteers
who prevented me to be off course for more than just a couple hundreds feet (thank you guys!!).</p>

<p>  <div style="width:image width px; font-size:80%; text-align:center;">
  <img src="http://gcalmettes.github.io/images/bandit50k-hotdoghill.jpg" alt="bandit 50K Hot Dog Hill"
  width=50%"width" height="height" style="padding-bottom:0.5em;" />
  <br/>The &ldquo;Hot Dog Hill&rdquo;<br>and the right turn entrance I almost missed</div></p>

<p>After some more hills during which I took care of my nutrition/hydration,
I approached the 15 mile half-course turnaround and I cheered
<a href="http://ultrarunnerrn.blogspot.com">Chris Price</a> who was already coming
back at me. He had a small 1-2 min lead on <a href="http://jameswalshracing.com">James Walsh</a>
and they both were looking very strong.
Chris Z was now in third place as he had passed both Keith and Kenneth.
Kenneth was actually still at the turnaround aid station when I arrived, 2:03 into the race.
I quickly re-filled my one handled, ate my last gel and thanked the volunteers
before heading back into the trail. I ran into <a href="http://j-tris.blogspot.com">Josh Spector</a>,
Trey Barnes and Margaret (leading woman),
on their way to the turnaround, and I cheered them on as well as all the following
other runners coming back at me.
It was great to see all those runners having a great time on the trail.</p>

<p>In the next uphill, I caught a brief glimpse of Keith,
and I calculated that I was just 3 min behind so I convinced myself to run harder.
My efforts didn&rsquo;t pay off as I still didn&rsquo;t catch him back when I hit the residential
neighborhood aid station (mile 20) for the second time of the day.
I quickly filled up my one handled with
electrolyte, and left the aid station with the idea of
pursuing my effort to close the gap. In my hurry, I completely
forgot to eat anything at the aid station and I didn&rsquo;t have any gels left.</p>

<p>The day was starting to get hot, and I attacked the last 5 miles climb of the day.
It was far from being a steep climb, but I didn&rsquo;t have the energy to run it at the pace I
wanted to, so I settled down into a slow-pace run. I was feeling really weak and my body was
begging for calories. I finally reached the top of the climb, thinking that I will be
able to ate some food while enjoying the killer view
on the surrounding mountains that this spot was offering.
Unfortunately the aid station at the top had water only
(Damnit!) but a volunteer told me that next aid station with food was just a
couple miles ahead. It was in fact the Hawaiian aid station I passed by at the
beginning of the day. Once there, I drank a lot of coke, ate two potatoes and some
salty pretzel, hoping to recover some of my energy.</p>

<p>  <div style="width:image width px; font-size:80%; text-align:center;">
  <img src="http://gcalmettes.github.io/images/bandit50k-wateraid.jpg" alt="bandit 50K aid station"
  width=80%"width" height="height" style="padding-bottom:0.5em;" />
  <br/>The aid station at the top of the last big climb.
  <br/>No Food, but killer view on the surrounding mountains!
  <br/>Photo <a href="http://www.allwedoisrun.com">Luis Escobar</a></div></p>

<p>I felt a little better, I thanked the awesome Hawaiian volunteers and started the
last descent back to Corriganville Park.
The descent was very rocky and technical, and I got passed by
Mike McMonagle in this section, just 1.5 mile to the finish, and I was seeing Matthew
also gaining on me.
Once at the bottom, I felt I had my energy back and I bombed on the last flat half
mile to finish in 6th place in 4:40 (2nd in Age Group), 30 min behind Chris Price
who set an amazing new course record.</p>

<p>  <div style="width:image width px; font-size:80%; text-align:center;">
  <img src="http://gcalmettes.github.io/images/bandit50k-prizzle.jpg" alt="bandit 50K win by Chris Price"
  width=70%"width" height="height" style="padding-bottom:0.5em;" />
  <br/>Congratulations to Chris Price for his amazing race and CR!
  <br/>Photo <a href="http://www.larunner.com">Billy Yang</a></div></p>

<p>After the finish, it was nice to introduced myself to and talked to all the local trail guys
(<a href="http://ultrarunnerrn.blogspot.com">Chris</a>, <a href="http://jameswalshracing.com">James</a>, Trey, <a href="http://www.larunner.com">Billy</a>, <a href="http://j-tris.blogspot.com">Josh</a>), they all are
amazing individuals.</p>

<p>I stayed a bit to cheer on the runners finishing their race and then thanked everyone
before leaving as I needed to return the rental car and go back
finishing some work at the lab.
This was really a really great Sunday! Organizers have put on a great event,
and for sure I will be back next year !</p>

<p>Some note learned during the race:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>messing up with nutrition in the second half of the race is not what you want to do</p></li>
<li><p>I need to integrate specific hill training sessions in my training and work on my downhill technique</p></li>
</ul>


<p>My next race is the <a href="http://www.lamarathon.com/">LA Marathon</a>.
This will force me to do more speed workouts, and to run at higher paces.
Hopefully this will be beneficial for
my future trail running races.</p>

<hr />
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[TNFC 50K 2012 - Race Report]]></title>
    <link href="http://gcalmettes.github.io/blog/2012/12/05/TNF50K/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-05T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://gcalmettes.github.io/blog/2012/12/05/TNF50K</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>  <div style="width:image width px; font-size:80%; text-align:center;">
  <img src="http://gcalmettes.github.io/images/tnf50-rain.jpg" alt="happy runner TNFC 50"
  width=80%"width" height="height" style="padding-bottom:0.5em;" />
  <br/>Happy runner under the rain</div></p>

<p>I am not sure why I decided to run the <a href="http://www.thenorthface.com/en_US/endurance-challenge/san-francisco-championship/?stop_mobi=yes">2012 The North Face Challenge Championship 50K</a>
as my first ever 50K trail race. I am not even sure why, a few months ago, I decided to give
a try to trail running. But anyways, I signed up to the race back in august just before it
sold out (yes, first hurdle successfully passed!).
The TNFC 50 event weekend is mostly famous for its 50 Mile race, which always gather
an exciting field of <a href="http://www.irunfar.com/2012/11/2012-the-north-face-50-mile-championships-mens-preview.html">Men</a> and <a href="http://www.irunfar.com/2012/11/2012-the-north-face-50-mile-championships-womens-preview.html">Women</a> elite runners, but as
a virgin of ultra trail distances, 50km looked long enough to me.</p>

<p>I had seen photos from last year event, and the trails in Marin Headlands
looked awesome, offering spectacular views over the Pacific Ocean.
Unfortunately, in the week leading up to the race, weather was calling for heavy rain and wind
and it was unlikely that we would run in the same <a href="http://www.irunfar.com/2011/12/2011-the-north-face-endurance-challenge-50-mile-results.html">perfect conditions</a> than the 2011
edition.
Confirmation of the bad news was given at the packet pick up
when the TNF staff announced
that California States Park officials had issued a mandatory re-route of both 50 Mile
and 50K race courses to ensure the safety of all runners, as considerable damages occurred
on California State Park trails due to weather.
As a result, the entire course north of Muir Beach (and the associated big climbs) was out
and the course was now basically a succession of smaller 800-1000ft hills.
Well, at least the race was still on!
(it happened that all the Sunday&rsquo;s races &mdash; 5k, 10k, &amp; half marathon &mdash; were cancelled)</p>

<p>  <div style="width:image width px; font-size:80%; text-align:center;">
  <img src="http://gcalmettes.github.io/images/tnf50-profile.jpg" alt="happy runner TNFC 50"
  width=90%"width" height="height" style="padding-bottom:0.5em;" />
  <br/>Profile of the 2012 TFNC 50K modified course</div></p>

<p>The next morning, I was up early, and headed out of my hotel room to catch
one of the shuttle to Fort Barry (the main event site).
Because of the heavy rain pounding the Marin Headlands, the start line area was
just mud everywhere and 45 min before the start I was already cold and soaked &hellip;
not really a good start ;) Still, I was excited to toe the line.</p>

<p>  <div style="width:image width px; font-size:80%; text-align:right;">
  <img src="http://gcalmettes.github.io/images/tnf50-start.jpg" alt="TNFC 50 start in the dark" align="right"
  width=40%"width" height="height" style="padding-bottom:0.5em; padding-left:0.5em" />
  </div></p>

<p>I didn&rsquo;t really have strong expectations for the race, but I was eager to see what my
limits were and I was ready to push myself as hard as I could.
My 3 months of solid training (relative to my standards) leading to the race had given
me confidence that I could break the 5:00 mark, and I decided that this would be my goal
for the race.</p>

<p>After <a href="http://www.ultramarathonman.com/web/">Dean Karnezes</a> gave us all a brief pep talk at the starting line, the race finally
went on! It was still dark, but a headlamp was not necessary as the sunlight was slowly showing
up. Surprisingly, I found myself running with the lead pack for the first mile.
After a quick look at my watch, I convinced myself that the pace we settled in
wasn&rsquo;t a good idea if I wanted to finish the course, so I let the group of
7-8 runners pulling away.
The first climb quickly arrived, and I was feeling good. Even if I wasn&rsquo;t pushing too hard
in the uphill, I came back on an passed a couple of runners.
However, as I was reaching the top of the climb,
I looked back and saw a group of 4-5 fast dudes charging behind me
and quickly closing the gap on me. As they arrived to my side, I realized that they
were the leaders of the 50 Mile race that started 2h earlier than the 50K,
and they were already in their second loop. I was now running
with some athletes of the Salomon Team, <a href="http://www.miguelheras.com/">Miguel Heras</a>, Greg Vollet,
François d'Haene, as well as <a href="https://twitter.com/mwolfepaw">Mike Wolfe</a> and  Cameron Clayton ;)
I couldn&rsquo;t maintain their speedy pace in the downhill for a long time though,
so quickly I was alone again, with a big smile on my face.</p>

<p>  <div style="width:image width px; font-size:80%; text-align:center;">
  <img src="http://gcalmettes.github.io/images/tnf50-withgreg.jpg" alt="Guillaume Calmettes and Greg Vollet"
  width=90%"width" height="height" style="padding-bottom:0.5em;" />
  <br/>Charging the downhill with Greg Vollet</div></p>

<p>The rest of the course was a succession of muddy climbs and slippery descents.
I felt good the whole race, running the uphills at a slow steady pace and rolling the
descents as best as I could.
I tried to take in 150-200 calories per hour, popping a gel every 30-45min,
and forced myself to drink regularly (even if I wasn&rsquo;t feeling thirsty because
of the rain).</p>

<p>The miles quickly passed without I noticed, and it was already the finish line!
5th overall in 4:14, 15min behind the winner, Joshua Korn from the team Salomon, I couldn&rsquo;t
ask for more! I threw my hands up in the air, being
so happy to have run further than I have had, especially in those flood-like conditions.</p>

<p>  <div style="width:image width px; font-size:80%; text-align:center;">
  <img src="http://gcalmettes.github.io/images/tnf50-joshua.jpg" alt="joshua korn TNFC 50"
  width=45%"width" height="height" style="padding-bottom:0.5em;" />
  <br/>Joshua Korn, winner of the TNFC 50K 2012
  <br/>Photo <a href="http://trappephoto.com">Matt Trappe</a></div></p>

<p>The food at the finish line area was really awesome, and I spend the next couple hours
cheering on the runners finishing their race. I missed the finish of the first 3 male
runners of the 50 Mile race, as they were already done when I finished my 50K,
but I had the chance to see the finish of the first female, <a href="http://emelieforsberg.com">Emilie Forsberg</a>
and her pacer, <a href="http://frostysfootsteps.wordpress.com">Anna Frost</a>.
Even if it was cold and rainy, the atmosphere at the finish line was awesome, trail
running is all about sharing with others! A lot of great memories!</p>

<p>What a great first 50K trail race! Time to start getting ready for 2013 now!</p>

<hr />
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
